<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: cmi | Zarrar's Journaling]]></title>
  <link href="http://czarrar.github.io/blog/categories/cmi/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://czarrar.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-11-12T16:03:18-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://czarrar.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Zarrar Shehzad]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Another Quick Pack Journey]]></title>
    <link href="http://czarrar.github.io/blog/2013/10/30/another-look-at-quick-pack-journey/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-30T15:55:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://czarrar.github.io/blog/2013/10/30/another-look-at-quick-pack-journey</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today, I&rsquo;ve got through a few things. First, I finished compiling the <code>regressors.csv</code> file for</p>

<p>Some minor things, I helped Krishna with some ROI error he had in CPAC. It turned out that his issue was due to incorrectly binarizing the mask.</p>

<h1>QuickPack</h1>

<p>Trying my hand again on quick pack today. Last time I got a bunch of different errors that I really couldn&rsquo;t track. I am re-running the complete run to see what errors I get again and try to figure those out. I&rsquo;m also rerunning the alff to see what happens there.</p>

<h2>Complete Run</h2>

<p>This appears to be re-running smoothly (knock on wood). The last time I ran a complete (preprocessing + derivatives) run, it led to some unclear problems.</p>

<h2>ALFF QP</h2>

<p>I get the same link error as I did before. The error occurs on line 562 in <code>utils.py</code> within the <code>create_symbolic_links</code>. The line and error are</p>

<pre><code>ext = fname.split('.', 1)[1]
IndexError: list index out of range
</code></pre>

<p>Basically <code>fname</code> should be a filename but a directory is passed instead and so it fails. Specifically, it appears to be passing <code>/home2/data/Projects/ABIDE_Initiative/CPAC/test_qp/ALFF_Output/pipeline_0/0051466_session_1/functional_freq_filtered/_scan_rest_1_rest/sinker_16</code>. I don&rsquo;t have much sense about what is going on with this file.</p>

<p>Other bits of information:</p>

<ul>
<li>The crash file is located <code>/home2/data/Projects/ABIDE_Initiative/CPAC/test_qp/crash/crash-20131030-145001-milham-link_16.a0.np
z</code>.</li>
<li>The directory in the working directory is <code>/data/Projects/ABIDE_Initiative/CPAC/test_qp/ALFF_Working/resting_preproc_0051466_session_1/_scan_rest_1_rest/link_16</code></li>
</ul>


<h3>Steve Talk</h3>

<p>I discussed this issue with Steve and it seems I will need to get down and dirty with nipype to understand the origin of this problem.</p>

<h2>REHO QP</h2>

<p>Here I got two errors. One of the errors was the same as with ALFF except instead of link_16 it is link_5. The other error is new and specific to REHO with the crash file: <code>/home2/data/Projects/ABIDE_Initiative/CPAC/test_qp/crash/crash-20131030-164123-milham-reho_map.a0.a0.npz</code>. It appears the error is an empty input filename being passed to the <code>compute_reho</code> in <code>reho/utils</code>.</p>

<p>A snapshot of the error is given below:</p>

<pre><code>/data/Projects/ABIDE_Initiative/CPAC/test_qp/Reho_Working/resting_preproc_0051466_session_1/reho_0/_scan_rest_1_rest/_scan_rest_1_rest/reho_map/&lt;string&gt; in compute_reho(in_file, mask_file, cluster_size)

/home/data/PublicProgram/epd-7.2-2-rh5-x86_64/lib/python2.7/site-packages/nibabel/loadsave.pyc in load(filename)
     37     except KeyError:
     38         raise ImageFileError('Cannot work out file type of "%s"' %
---&gt; 39                              filename)
     40     if ext in ('.nii', '.mnc', '.mgh', '.mgz'):
     41         klass = class_map[img_type]['class']

ImageFileError: Cannot work out file type of ""
Interface Function failed to run. 
</code></pre>

<p>To run the crash file, see the code below.</p>

<p>``` python
import sys
sys.path.insert(0, &lsquo;/home2/data/Projects/CPAC_Regression_Test/nipype-installs/fcp-indi-nipype/running-install/lib/python2.7/site-packages&rsquo;)
sys.path.insert(1, &ldquo;/home2/data/Projects/CPAC_Regression_Test/2013-05-30_cwas/C-PAC&rdquo;)
import CPAC
import CPAC.reho.utils
from nipype.utils.filemanip import loadflat</p>

<p>crashinfo = loadflat(&ldquo;/home2/data/Projects/ABIDE_Initiative/CPAC/test_qp/crash/crash-20131030-164123-milham-reho_map.a0.a0.npz&rdquo;)
crashinfo[&lsquo;node&rsquo;].run()
```</p>

<h1>Preprocessing EmotionalBS</h1>

<p>I am going to preprocess the emotionalBS data again with CPAC+ANTS. Some relevant parameters are:</p>

<ul>
<li>Used ANTS for registration</li>
<li>Two nuisance correction strategies

<pre><code>  * compcor+motion+linear+quadratic
  * compcor+global+motion+linear+quadratic
</code></pre></li>
<li>Both frequency filtering (0.01-0.1 Hz) and no filtering</li>
<li>Smoothing of 4.5mm (only for derivatives)</li>
<li>Generated some SCA and drSCA based derivates using ROIs/maps from the ABIDE preprocessing. Otherwise no other derivatives were created.</li>
</ul>


<h2>Install FSL 5 for Gelert</h2>

<p>I was a little confused on how to install fsl 5 to a custom path (<code>/home2/data/PublicProgram</code>). It seemed to go through neurodebian and apt-get, I needed certain admin privileges that even Mike&rsquo;s account didn&rsquo;t have. And even if I had those, it wasn&rsquo;t clear how I would install to a custom directory. Then I realized I could just copy the current fsl5 in <code>/usr/share/fsl/5.o</code> into that directory. The reason for this (<code>/home2/data/PublicProgram</code>) directory is so</p>

<h1>New Journal</h1>

<p>I also worked on setting up this blog/journal with github user account. The goal is to chronicle my work efforts with particular thought on any issues I encounter. A major side benefit will be easier communication with others in the lab (e.g., was able to easily show the error for ALFF quick pack to Steve). Previously, I had been using different journal pages for each of my projects. I ended up being a big confused where to post stuff and often lost track of the markdown pages that I had created before they were published. With one journal site, this should all be easier.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m also testing out this slightly different jekyll wrapper (octopress). I unfortunately spent a lot longer (2 hours) setting it up cuz of a git error then I had wanted. So I hope some of its benefits over jekyll bootstrap such as easier syncing, simpler interface, and simpler integration of more advanced plugins, will be useful in the long run. That way I can justify my time spent installing it!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
